Finding Aid for the Yuji Ichioka Papers LSC.0242
UCLA Library Special Collections
Yuji Ichioka papers
circa 1880-2002
UCLA Library Special Collections
Ichioka, Yuji
LSC.0242
681.0 Linear Feet (162 boxes and 2 oversize boxes)
Yuji Ichioka (1936-2002) was an American-born Japanese (Nisei) historian who pioneered in studies of Japanese American experiences. Coining the term "Asian American," Ichioka was also instrumental in developing an academic field of Asian American Studies since the late 1960s. The 2009 addition to the original Ichioka papers (processed in 2005) consists of personal documents, materials relating to the establishment and initial operation of the UCLA Asian American Studies Center, Ichioka's involvement in the early phase of an ethnic studies program at UC Berkeley and community activism in northern and southern California, correspondence, conference planning and participations, publication drafts, research materials, teaching materials, and subject files.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS DIGITAL MATERIALS: This collection contains both processed and unprocessed digital materials. Digital materials are not currently available for access, unless otherwise noted in a Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note at the series and file levels. All requests to access processed digital materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Emma Gee, 2005.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9953411593606533
Biography
Yuji Ichioka (1936-2002) was born in San Francisco, California, as a son of Japanese immigrants. Having interned at the Topaz internment camp in Utah during the Pacific War, he returned to the San Francisco bay area with his parents and siblings to start a new life in Berkeley, where he stayed until his high school graduation in 1954. Ichioka then served in the United States Army to station in Germany, and after his discharge, he attended UCLA and graduated in 1962. Intending to pursue graduate study in Chinese history with a fellowship from Columbia University, Ichioka moved to New York City, but he quit the program soon after. Having served as a youth parole worker with the New York State Training School for Boys, he traveled to Japan for the first time in the winter of 1966, an experience that inspired him to take up the study of Japanese language and pursue research on Japanese immigrant experience in the United States. After he returned from the trans-Pacific trip, Ichioka enrolled in an MA program in Japanese history at the University of California at Berkeley, which he completed in 1968. Around this time, he also played a central role in forming the Asian American Political Alliance, and Ichioka, along with his partner Emma Gee whom he had met at Columbia, steered the younger generations of Asian Americans to a civil right/antiwar movement. Recruited as the instructor of the first Asian American studies course at UCLA, Ichioka took part in the establishment of the UCLA Asian American Studies Center while maintaining his ties to early leaders in UC Berkeley's ethnic studies. By 1972, Ichioka permanently moved to southern California, where he continued his research and writing on Japanese American history until his death in September 2002. At UCLA he was Research Associate and Adjunct Associate Professor of History. Ichioka was married to Emma Gee, a scholar of Asian American woman history, as well as a writer and labor activist.
During his career as a professional historian, Ichioka traveled numerous times to Japan for research and teaching while writing two major monographs: The Issei: The World of the First Generation Japanese Immigrants, 1885-1924 (1988), and Before Internment: Essays in Prewar Japanese American History (posthumously published in 2006). Other publications of his include; 2 edited volumes: Karl G. Yoneda, Ganbatte: Sixty-Year Struggle of a Kibei Worker (1983), and Views from Within: The Japanese American Evacuation and Resettlement Study (1989); 2 annotated bibliographies: A Buried Past (1974), and A Buried Past II (1999); and a dozens of path-breaking journal articles in Amerasia Journal, Pacific Historical Review, Agricultural History, and California History, among others. Ichioka was among the first few Asian Americanists who showed an interest in studies of Asian immigration to Latin America when such a subject was unconceivable in the field, and he took a few trips to Peru and Brazil for networking and preliminary research for a comparative study project and international conference on Japanese in the Americas.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of Yuji Ichioka's correspondence (1970-2002), research papers, writings, teaching materials, rare Japanese American periodicals, and miscellaneous subject files. The research papers contain photocopies of Japanese immigrant publications and newspaper clippings, Japanese diplomatic papers, American and Japanese magazine articles, and U.S. National Archives materials, which are related to various aspects of Japanese American experiences running mainly from the 1880s to 1945. Though these materials provided a basis for the writing of his articles and books, there are great deals of primary sources that are untapped and therefore help researchers pursue original historical studies. Researchers should be also aware that because Ichioka periodically deposited some of his research acquisitions, especially Japanese American personal papers and rare books, as part of UCLA's Japanese American Research Project collections, the materials included in this collection constitute only portions of what Ichioka had collected for over thirty years of his career. Drafts and revision notes of Ichioka's published articles and books are included in this collection, as the instructional materials that he developed are also available. His professional correspondence, albeit closed for use for ten years from accession, would be useful for understanding Ichioka's day-to-day operation as a scholar and teacher, his service to the fields of Japanese American history and Asian American Studies, and his interactions with scholars and intellectuals in not only the United States but also Latin America and Japan. Others papers pertain to Ichioka's role in the development of Asian American archival collections at UCLA and the organization of academic conferences
The 2009 addition represents the materials that have been discovered at Ichioka's residence since the original acquisition was processed in 2005. This collection of 23 boxes consists of Yuji Ichioka's personal files (inc. school materials), papers relating to the establishment and operation of the UCLA Asian American Studies Center, the first Asian American studies course he taught there in 1969, his involvement in the nascent phase of UC Berkeley's ethnic studies program and community-based political organizing in northern and southern California, correspondence, materials pertaining to conference planning and participations, publication manuscripts and drafts, research materials, teaching materials, and miscellaneous subject files. Most of the listing categories used for the organization of this collection are drawn from the original 2005 collection, though a few new categories are created. The most notable of those new categories are the first two container lists, which provide a good glimpse into Ichioka's formative education at UCLA and UC Berkeley, as well as his role in the development of the UCLA Asian American Studies Center. Because his involvement in-and commitment to-community activism was closely tied to his scholarly activities with the Asian American Studies Center, the materials relating to these matters are placed side by side in the second category of Container List, and researchers should be aware of their inseparable nature. It is also notable that the materials in the same category include those produced by and relating to Emma Gee, who worked together with Ichioka in the Asian American movement. The materials pertaining to the planning of and the networking for a comparative study of Japanese in North and South America would be also valuable in light of Ichioka's pioneering vision for this area of transnational historical research. Whereas the 2009 addition supplements the original acquisition with the hitherto unavailable documents covering the birth of the Asian American Studies Center at UCLA and an international study of Japanese in the Americas, many of the research papers in this collection overlap with the contents of the latter, and so do the research materials. (The finding aid provides cross-reference information when necessary.) Still, some of his writings and research materials in this collection not only reveal a birds' eye view of Ichioka's scholarly endeavor, but they also represent the primary sources that are untapped and therefore potentially quite helpful for researchers in their own studies. It should be noted that because Ichioka periodically deposited some of his research acquisitions, especially Japanese American personal papers and rare books, as part of UCLA's Japanese American Research Project collections and the East Asian Library holdings, the materials included in this-and the earlier 2005-collection constitute only portions of what Ichioka had collected for over thirty years of his career. The correspondence files in Boxes 145 and 146, as those in Boxes 1 through 16, are closed for ten years and restricted for use. Eiichiro Azuma processed both the 2005 and 2009 acquisitions.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Correspondence File
Conferences and Edited Anthologies
Publications
Research Materials
Teaching Materials
Archival Development
Subject Files
Periodicals
Asian American Studies & Movement
Card Catalog
Personal File
Related Material
The 2005 acquisition of Ichioka's office materials-consisting of 139 boxes-is the backbone of the newly-expanded Yuji Ichioka Papers. Many other collections of manuscripts were also deposited by Ichioka as part of the Japanese American Research Project collections at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Library, UCLA. Japanese American Research Project Collections at Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Library, UCLA. See Yuji Ichioka, el al., A Buried Past: An Annotated Bibliography of the Japanese American Research Project Collection (Berkeley: University of California Press, 1974); and Yuji Ichioka and Eiichiro Azuma, A Buried Past II: A Sequel to the Annotated Bibliography of the Japanese American Research Project Collection (Los Angeles: UCLA Asian American Studies Center, 1999).
Japanese Americans -- History -- Archives.; Ichioka, Yuji--Archives.
- Correspondence
  - Incoming
    - 1970-1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1982 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1983 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - January-May 1985 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - June-September 1985 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - October-December 1985 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - January-February 1986 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - March-April 1986 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - May-July 1986 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - August-October 1986 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - November-December 1986 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - January-February 1987 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - March-May 1987 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - June-August 1987 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - September-December 1987 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - January-March 1988 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - April-June 1988 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - July-August 1988 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - September-October 1988 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - November-December 1988 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - January-February 1989 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - March-April 1989 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - April-May 1989 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - June-July 1989 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - August-October 1989 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - November-December 1989 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - January-April 1990 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - May-August 1990 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - September-December 1990 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - January-February 1991 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - March 1991 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - April-May 1991 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - June-July 1991 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Incoming Correspondence, August-September 1991 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - October-December 1991 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - January-February 1992 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - March-May 1992 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - June-August 1992 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - September-December 1992 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - January-February 1993 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - March-May 1993 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - June-July 1993 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - August-October 1993 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - November-December 1993 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - January-March 1994 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - April-June 1994 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - July-September 1994 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - October-December 1994 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - January-February 1995 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - March-May 1995 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - June-August 1995 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - September-October 1995 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - November-December 1995 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - January-February 1996 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - March-May 1996 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - May-July 1996 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - August-December 1996 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - January-April 1997 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - April-August 1997 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - September-December 1997 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - January-March 1998 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - March-June 1998 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - July-September 1998 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - October-December 1998 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - January-April 1999 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - April-June 1999 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - July-December 1999 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - 2000 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - January-July 2001 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - August-December 2001 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - 2002 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Incoming Correspondence., December 1989-February 1990, November 1992 (Box 145, Folder 9)
      General note
      [Portions of Boxes 145-146 are CLOSED for ten years and RESTRICTED for use.]
    - Incoming Correspondence., 1995, 1996, 1997 (sporadic) (Box 145, Folder 10)
    - Incoming Correspondence., July, November-December 1999 (Box 145, Folder 11)
    - Incoming Correspondence., January-June 2000 (Box 145, Folder 12)
    - Incoming Correspondence., July-December 2000 (Box 146, Folder 1)
    - Incoming Correspondence., 2000-2001, May 2002 (Box 146, Folder 2)
  - Outgoing
    - 1976-1979 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - 1982-1983 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - 1984-1985 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - 1986 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - 1987 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - 1988 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - 1989 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - January-May 1990 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - June-December 1990 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - January-May 1991 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - June-December 1991 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - January-May 1992 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - June-December 1992 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - 1993 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - 1994 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - 1995 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - 1996 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - 1997 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - 1998 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - 1999-2002 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Outgoing Correspondence., January 1990, 1997, 1999-2001 (sporadic) (Box 146, Folder 3)
- Conferences and Edited Anthologies
  - "Coming of Age in the Thirties"
    - Correspondence with CCH (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence with Tamura Norio (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Incoming Letters, December 1984-May 1985 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Incoming Letters, June-December 1985 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Outgoing Letters, December 1984-September 1985 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Administrative Papers (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Papers pertaining to Accounting (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Papers pertaining to CCH Reimbursements (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - CCH Evaluations by Conference Participants (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Conference Participants' Curricula Vitae (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Conference Papers (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Conference Papers (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Conference Programs (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Press Releases (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Newspaper Clippings (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Conference Photographs (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - "Fifty Years After the Pacific War"
    - Conference Correspondence, 1995 (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Conference Papers (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - Conference Fliers, Press Releases, and Newspaper Clippings (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - Frank Hirata Essay and Photograph (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - Sen Nishiyama Essay, Correspondence, and Photograph (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - John J. Stephan Essay Drafts, Correspondence, and Photographs (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - Kay Tateishi Essay Drafts and Correspondence (Box 24, Folder 7)
    - Mary Tomita Essay Drafts, Correspondence, and Photographs (Box 24, Folder 8)
    - Nobuyo Yamane Essay Drafts, Correspondence, and Photographs (Box 24, Folder 9)
  - "Views From Within"
    - Columbia Foundation File (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - CCH Correspondence and Grant Application (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - CCH Miscellaneous Forms (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - CCH Vouchers (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - California Bicentennial Foundation for U.S. Constitution File (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Conference Themes (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Conference Correspondence, November 1985-April 1986 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Conference Correspondence, May 1986-January 1987 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Conference Correspondence, February-November 1987 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Conference Participants Curricula Vitae (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Conference Papers, A-H (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - Conference Papers, I-Z (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous Administrative Papers (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Conference Programs (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Press Releases and Leaflets (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Newspaper Clippings and Photographs (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Anthology Editorial Correspondence, A-K (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Anthology Editorial Correspondence, L-S (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - Anthology Editorial Correspondence, T-W (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - Book Reviews (Box 20, Folder 9)
    - Drafts of Ichioka's Introduction, Preface, Table of Contents, and Index (Box 20, Folder 10)
    - Essay Draft: Brian Hayashi (Box 20, Folder 11)
    - Essay Drafts: Lane and James Hirabayashi (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Essay Drafts: Charles Kikuchi (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - Essay Drafts: Frank Miyamoto (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Essay Drafts: Frank Miyamoto (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - Essay Drafts: Gary Okihiro (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Essay Drafts: James Sakoda (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Essay Drafts: James Sakoda (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - Essay Drafts: James Sakoda (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - Essay Drafts: Robert Spencer (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - Essay Drafts: Peter Suzuki (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - Essay Drafts: Dana Takagi (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - Anthology Final Manuscript, Introduction to Chapter 3 (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - Anthology Final Manuscript, Chapter 4 to Chapter 7 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - Anthology Final Manuscript, Chapter 8 to Chapter 10 (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - Anthology Page Proofs, Part I (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - Anthology Page Proofs, Part II and Part III (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - Anthology Page Proof Extras (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Anthology Page Proof Extras (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Anthology Unbound Copy for Proof (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - Papers pertaining to Violet Kazue de Cristoforo (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - Materials relating to the Views From Within conference. UC Berkeley, September 1987 (Box 146, Folder 4)
- Publications
  - A Buried Past
    - "Bibliographical Research Proposal" and Correspondence (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - Lists of JARP materials and working bibliographies (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - Working Drafts, ca. 1973 (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - Yuji Ichioka, et al., A Buried Past (1974) (Box 27, Folder 7)
    - Draft of Introduction for A Buried Past., December 1970 (Box 146, Folder 5)
      (See also Box 27, Folder 6.)
  - Articles
    - "The 1921 Turlock Incident," 1972-1976 (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - "Japanese Associations and the Japanese Government," 1975 (Box 30, Folder 3)
    - "Japanese Associations and the Japanese Government," 1976 (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - "Japanese Associations and the Japanese Government" Pacific Historical Review (1977) (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - "The Legacy of Struggle and Disillusionment," draft, 1976 (Box 30, Folder 6)
    - "Jido Kyoiku Mondai," draft, 1976 (Box 30, Folder 7)
    - "Ameyuki-san" Amerasia Journal (1977) (Box 30, Folder 8)
    - "Ukeoi-Gyosha," draft, 1977 (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - "The Early Japanese Immigrant Quest for Citizenship" Amerasia Journal (1977) (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - "The Dekasegi-Shosei," draft, 1977 (Box 31, Folder 3)
    - "Asian Immigrant Coal Miners," drafts, 1978 (Box 31, Folder 4)
    - "Asian Immigrant Coal Miners," draft (1978) and published version (1979) (Box 31, Folder 5)
    - "An Abortive Instance of Japanese Labor Diplomacy," 1978 (Box 31, Folder 6)
    - "An Instance of Private Japanese Diplomacy," draft (1981) and published version (1983) (Box 31, Folder 7)
    - "Amerika Nadeshiko," drafts (1979) and published version (1980) (Box 31, Folder 8)
    - "Changing Concepts and Approaches," drafts, 1980-1982 (Box 31, Folder 9)
    - "Japanese Immigrant Nationalism," 1981 (Box 32, Folder 1)
    - "Japanese Immigrant Nationalism," 1981 (Box 32, Folder 2)
    - "Japanese Immigrant Nationalism," drafts (1989) and published version (1990) (Box 32, Folder 3)
    - "Shikatsu Mondai" draft (1983) and published version (1984) (Box 32, Folder 4)
    - "Recent Japanese Scholarship," draft, 1983 (Box 32, Folder 5)
    - "A Nisei Critique of Futatsu no Sokoku," published versions (1984) (Box 32, Folder 6)
    - "Abiko Kyutaro," draft (1984) and published version (1985) (Box 32, Folder 7)
    - "Abiko Kyutaro," Japanese translations, ca. 1986 (Box 32, Folder 8)
    - "Abiko Kyutaro," published Japanese version (1986) (Box 33, Folder 1)
    - "Attorney for the Defense," drafts, 1984-1985 (Box 33, Folder 2)
    - "Attorney for the Defense" Pacific Historical Review (1986) (Box 33, Folder 3)
    - "A Study in Dualism," drafts, 1984-1985 (Box 33, Folder 4)
    - "A Study in Dualism," Amerasia Journal (1986-87) (Box 33, Folder 5)
    - "Dai-Nisei Mondai," drafts, 1984, 1987 (Box 33, Folder 6)
    - "Dai-Nisei Mondai," drafts, 1987 (Box 34, Folder 1)
    - "Dai-Nisei Mondai," Japanese translation, 1988 (Box 34, Folder 2)
    - "Dai-Nisei Mondai," Japanese page proofs, 1988, 1991 (Box 34, Folder 3)
    - "Dai-Nisei Mondai," published Japanese version (1991) (Box 34, Folder 4)
    - "Unity Within Diversity," drafts (1986) and published version (1987) (Box 35, Folder 1)
    - "Kengakudan," draft (1992) and published version (1994) (Box 35, Folder 2)
    - "The Backfiring of a Strategy," draft, 1994 (Box 35, Folder 3)
    - "The Meaning of Loyalty" drafts (1995) and published version (1997) (Box 35, Folder 4)
    - "The Death of Dr. Honda Rikita," drafts (1997) and published version (1997) (Box 35, Folder 5)
    - Various unpublished essay drafts, ca. 1995-1998 (Box 35, Folder 6)
    - "A Historian by Happenstance," draft (1999) and published version (2000) (Box 35, Folder 7)
    - Yuji Ichioka miscellaneous writings, 1988-1999 (Box 35, Folder 8)
  - Book Reviews
    - 1970-1984 (Box 36, Folder 1)
    - 1986-1991 (Box 36, Folder 2)
    - 1992-2000 (Box 36, Folder 3)
  - Ganbatte
    - Correspondence with Karl G. Yoneda, February 1980-August 1984 (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - Papers pertaining to Editorial Matter (Box 28, Folder 2)